# Ramakrishnan Sundara Raman

PhD Candidate, University of Michigan

**Ü** Updated: 26 June 2023

I am a PhD candidate with 5+ years of experience in computer security and networking research, with expertise in using Internet measurement methods to detect, analyze and prevent large-scale threats to Internet users' security and privacy. My research involves longitudinally measuring Internet censorship and network interference at global scale, and examining the technologies that enable censorship and surveillance. I lead work on the Censored Planet Observatory, which is a platform for measuring various types of network interference continuously around the world, and I am the recipient of an OTF Information Controls Fellowship, Rackham Predoctoral Fellowship, and an IRTF Applied Networking Research Prize.

# **Education**

2018 – Present PhD Candidate, University of Michigan in Computer Science and Engineering

Advisor: Prof. Rova Ensafi

Thesis title: Global, Longitudinal, and Data-Driven Investigation of Network Censor-

ship

**CGPA:** 3.95 out of 4

2013 – 2017 **Bachelor of Technology, Vellore Institute of Technology** in Computer Science and

Engineering

Project Title: Measuring Last-Mile Internet Reliability During Severe Weather

CGPA: 9.69 out of 10 Rank in CSE: 2 out of 648

# **Conference Publications**

Global, Passive Detection of Connection Tampering
 R. Sundara Raman, L.H. Merino, K. Bock, M. Fayed, D. Levin, N. Sullivan, L. Valenta

 ACM SIGCOMM, September 2023

Network Responses to Russia's Invasion of Ukraine in 2022: A Cautionary Tale for Internet Freedom

R. Ramesh\*, **R. Sundara Raman\***, A. Virkud, A. Dirksen, A. Huremagic, D. Fifield, D. Rodenburg, R. Hynes, D. Madory, R. Ensafi

USENIX Security Symposium, August 2023

• https://ramakrishnansr.com/assets/russia-ukraine-invasion.pdf

Detecting DNS Manipulation using TLS Certificates

E. Tsai, D. Kumar, **R. Sundara Raman**, G. Li, Y. Eiger, R. Ensafi Privacy Enhancing Technologies Symposium (PETS), July 2023

♦ https://ramakrishnansr.com/assets/certainty.pdf

Network Measurement Methods for Locating and Examining Censorship Devices

R. Sundara Raman\*, M. Wang\*, J.Dalek, J. Mayer, and R. Ensafi

ACM Conference on emerging Networking EXperiments and Technologies (CoNEXT), December 2022

TRTF Applied Networking Research Prize

• https://ramakrishnansr.com/assets/censorship\_devices.pdf

A Large-scale Investigation into Geodifferences in Mobile Apps

R. Kumar, A. Virkud, <u>R. Sundara Raman</u>, A. Prakash, and R. Ensafi USENIX Security Symposium, August 2022

♦ https://ramakrishnansr.com/assets/appmap.pdf

O Lost in Transmission: Investigating Filtering of COVID-19 Websites

A. Vyas, **R. Sundara Raman**, N. Ceccio, P. Lutscher, and R. Ensafi Financial Cryptography and Data Security (FC), March 2021

• https://ramakrishnansr.com/assets/covid.pdf

<sup>\*</sup>Both authors contributed equally to this research

#### O Censored Planet: An Internet-wide, Longitudinal Censorship Observatory

R. Sundara Raman, P. Shenoy, K. Kohls, and R. Ensafi

ACM Conference on Computer and Communications Security (CCS), November 2020

• https://ramakrishnansr.com/assets/censoredplanet.pdf

## O Investigating Large Scale HTTPS Interception in Kazakhstan

**R. Sundara Raman**, L. Evdokimov, E. Wustrow, A. Halderman, and R. Ensafi ACM Internet Measurement Conference (IMC), October 2020

P Best Paper Award Nominee

♦ https://ramakrishnansr.com/assets/Kazakhstan.pdf

# O Measuring the Deployment of Network Censorship Filters at Global Scale

R. Sundara Raman, A. Stoll, J. Dalek, R. Ramesh, W. Scott, R. Ensafi

Network and Distributed System Security Symposium (NDSS), February 2020

• https://ramakrishnansr.com/assets/filtermap.pdf

#### O Decentralized Control: A Case Study of Russia

R. Ramesh, <u>R. Sundara Raman</u>, M. Bernhard, V. Ongkowijaya, L. Evdokimov, A. Edmundson, S. Sprecher, M. Ikram, R. Ensafi

Network and Distributed System Security Symposium (NDSS), February 2020

TCSAW'20 Applied Research Competition North America Top 10 Paper

• https://ramakrishnansr.com/assets/russia.pdf

# **Workshop Publications**

# Advancing the Art of Censorship Data Analysis

R. Sundara Raman, A. Virkud, S. Laplante, V. Fortuna, R. Ensafi

Free and Open Communications on the Internet (FOCI), February 2023

https://ramakrishnansr.com/assets/censorship-data-analysis.pdf

# A Multi-Perspective View of Internet Censorship in Myanmar

R. Padmanabhan, A. Filastò, M. Xynou, <u>R. Sundara Raman</u>, K. Middleton, M. Zhang, D. Madory, M. Roberts, and A. Dainotti

Free and Open Communications on the Internet (FOCI), August 2021

• https://ramakrishnansr.com/assets/myanmar.pdf

#### **Awards**

### Research

# IRTF Applied Networking Research Prize (ANRP) 2023

January 2023

https://www.ietf.org/blog/anrp-2023/

#### ■ HotPETs 2022 Best Talk Award

July 2022

https://petsymposium.org/best-hotpets-talks.php

# ■ University of Michigan CSE Graduate Student Honors Runners Up Award November 2020

₱ https://cse.engin.umich.edu/stories/2020-cse-graduate-student-honors-competition-highlights-outstanding-research

# ■ ACM IMC 2020 Best Paper Award Nominee

October 2020

#### Fellowships

#### Rackham Predoctoral Fellowship

March 2023

• https://cse.engin.umich.edu/stories/ram-sundara-raman-earns-rackham-predoctoral-fellowship

#### OTF Information Controls Fellowship (ICFP) Award

November 2021

♦ https://www.opentech.fund/about/people/ramakrishnan-sundara-raman/

Teaching & Service

#### North Campus Deans' MLK Spirit Award 2023

January 2023

♦ https://culture.engin.umich.edu/2023-nominees-recipients/

# ■ University of Michigan CSE GSI Honorable Mention Award August 2021

♦ https://ramakrishnansr.com/images/honorable\_mention\_award.pdf

Grants

#### ACM IMC 2022 Travel Grant

October 2022

#### DARPA MICE Grant

Title: Leveraging machine learning to build an intelligent Censored Planet observatory

August 2021

# ■ USENIX Security 2020 Student Grant

August 2020

# ■ Citizen Lab Summer Institute (CLSI) 2019 Travel Grant

August 2019

# **Teaching**

Topic: Censorship and Circumvention

January 2023 – April 2023 Substitute Instructor, EECS 588, University of Michigan

Topic: Computer and Network Security

Topic: Censorship and Circumvention

August 2020 – December 2020 Graduate Student Instructor (GSI), EECS 588, University of Michigan

Topic: Computer and Network Security

GSI Honorable Mention Award

# **Work Experience**

July 2022 - September 2022

#### Research Intern, Cloudflare Inc.

- Designed and implemented a large network monitoring system that identifies anomalous network events such as connection tampering attacks in large-scale network traffic at the rate of millions of packets per second.
- Developed network data analysis methods and tools for detecting large-scale traffic tampering passively from an operator's point of view.
- Built production dashboards and reports showcasing significant network events such as the effects of the protests in Iran on Internet traffic.

November 2021 - July 2022

# OTF Senior ICFP Fellow in Information Controls, The Citizen Lab

- Researched novel measurement methods for locating and examining network devices that performed surveillance and censorship.
- Collaborated with the expert team at the Citizen Lab, a research group focused on network forensics.
- Published several open-source tools and fingerprint datasets for identifying censorship devices.

July 2017 - May 2018

#### Associate Consultant, Microsoft Global Delivery

Contributed to large enterprise systems for business applications that can deliver value to large organizations around the world.

March 2017 – July 2017

# Research Intern, University of Maryland

Advisor: Prof. Neil Spring

- Facilitated a measurement platform and analysis tools that identifies last-mile residential Internet outages in areas affected by severe weather conditions in real-time.
- Poster presented at ACM Internet Measurement Conference 2017:
   "Measuring Last-Mile Internet Reliability During Severe Weather"

May 2016 - July 2016

## ■ Intern, Microsoft Global Delivery

Integrated data analytics into Microsoft's project management tool, built on ASP.NET. Microsoft's Power BI tool was utilized to make interactive reports that provided valuable insight to the users.

# **Mentoring**

- Undergraduate Students: Yusei Uehara (2023), Gavin Li (2021 2023), Apurva Virkud (2020 2022),
   Anjali Vyas (2020 2021), Nick Ceccio (2020 2021), Prerana Shenoy (2019 2020), Victor Ongkowijaya (2018 2019), Adrian Stoll (2018 2019)
- Graduate Students: Shreyas Chandrashekaran (2023), Kyle Astroth (2023), Anna Ablove (2022 2023), Elisa Tsai (2020 - 2023)

### **Talks**

- Workshop Talk: Advancing the Art of Censorship Data Analysis
   Free and Open Communications on the Internet (FOCI), February 2023
- Lightning Talk: Exploring Internet censorship through the Censored Planet Dashboard
   Open Technology Fund (OTF), January 2023
- Conference Talk: Network Measurement Methods for Locating and Examining Network Censorship Devices

Conference on emerging Networking EXperiments and Technologies (CoNEXT 2022), December 2022

- Workshop Talk: Improving Usability of Internet Censorship Data through a Censorship Dashboard
   15th Workshop on Hot Topics in Privacy Enhancing Technologies (HotPETs), July 2022
  - Best Talk Award
- Tech Demo: Exploring Internet censorship with the Censored Planet Dashboard RightsCon 2022, June 2022
  - ₱ https://youtu.be/j1sLWAmOnMA
- Symposium Talk: Censored Planet: An Internet-wide, Longitudinal Censorship Observatory
   The 5th Annual Data for Public Good Symposium, March 2022
  - $\pmb{\mathscr{O}} \text{ https://midas.umich.edu/2022-d4pg/research-talks/\#research-talks}$
- Invited Talk: Censored Planet Community Webinar 2021

Censored Planet, October 2021

- f https://youtu.be/v5G\_nUUzVv8
- Invited Talk: Censored Planet: An Internet-wide Longitudinal Observatory NDSS DNS Privacy Workshop (DNSPriv), February 2021
- Conference Talk: Censored Planet: An Internet-wide Longitudinal Observatory
   ACM Conference on Computer and Communications Security (CCS), November 2020
   https://youtu.be/8dwZdNkJ508
- Conference Talk: Investigating Large Scale HTTPS Interception in Kazakhstan ACM Internet Measurement Conference (IMC), October 2020
   https://youtu.be/RoYWsfNOCr4
- Invited Talk: Censored Planet: Measuring Internet censorship remotely OONI Internet Measurement Village (IMV), June 2020
  - ₱ https://youtu.be/5IgnvR42cMQ

Conference Talk: Measuring the Deployment of Network Censorship Filters at Global Scale
Network and Distributed System Security Symposium (NDSS), February 2020
 https://youtu.be/R8V1H0wakQk

# **Reports and Blogposts**

Making Censorship Data More User Friendly

Internet Society Pulse Blog, May 2023

• https://pulse.internetsociety.org/blog/making-censorship-data-more-user-friendly

Profiling Internet Censors: Methods to Measure and Locate Censorship Devices

Open Technology Fund (OTF), December 2022

• https://www.opentech.fund/news/profiling-internet-censors-methods-to-measure-and-locate-censorship-devices/

O An analysis of a large-scale HTTPS interception

APNIC Blog, February 2021

♦ https://blog.apnic.net/2021/02/15/an-analysis-of-a-large-scale-https-interception/

 US Government and military websites are geoblocked from Hong Kong and China Censored Planet, August 2020

• https://censoredplanet.org/hongkong

## **Posters**

- Censored Planet: An Internet-wide, Longitudinal Censorship Observatory Midwest Security Workshop, April 2019
- Measuring Last Mile Internet Reliability During Severe Weather ACM Internet Measurement Conference (IMC), November 2017

# **Certifications**

O 2023 Rackham-CRLT Preparing Future Faculty Seminar

University of Michigan, June 2023

• https://ramakrishnansr.com/assets/pff2023.pdf

Introduction to Data Science in Python

University of Michigan Coursera, June 2023

♦ https://ramakrishnansr.com/assets/coursera-intro-data-science-python.pdf

# **Service**

Chairing

Session Chair at FOCI'21

♦ https://conferences.sigcomm.org/sigcomm/2021/workshop-foci.html

Reviewing

TPC Member, IEEE Symposium on Security and Privacy (S&P) 2024

Phttps://sp2024.ieee-security.org/cfpapers.html

- Reviewer, 6th International Conference on Computer Science and Application Engineering (CSAE) 2022
- TPC Member, ACM SIGCOMM 2021 Workshop on Free and Open Communications on the Internet (FOCI)

♦ https://conferences.sigcomm.org/sigcomm/2021/workshop-foci.html

External Reviewing

- **USENIX Security Symposium 2022**
- ACM Internet Measurement Conference (IMC) 2021
- USENIX Security Symposium 2021
- ACM Internet Measurement Conference (IMC) 2020

- IEEE Symposium on Security and Privacy (S&P) 2020
- Privacy Enhancing Technology Symposium (PETS) 2020
- **USENIX Security Symposium 2019**
- IEEE Symposium on Security and Privacy (S&P) 2019

# Leadership

Outreach Chair at CSEG, UM CSE graduate student organization
June 2020 – May 2022

My responsibilities included arranging and managing outreach events throughout the year that aimed at spreading knowledge about computer science research in various schools, colleges and groups. I also participated as the DEI committee student representative of CSEG in the first few months of 2022.

- To Deans' MLK Spirit Award 2023
- Administrator of the Security Reading Group (SECRIT) in UM CSE June 2019 June 2021

# References

Roya Ensafi, Assistant Professor, University of Michigan